So we've covered risks and
how they affect a project,
but we haven't fully discussed
dependencies—arguably one of
the biggest factors in a project.
In this video, we'll discuss
dependencies—both internal and external—how
to identify and track them,
as well as their importance.
There are a few different
types of dependencies, and
we'll discuss a few examples of each one.
So what exactly are dependencies?
Dependencies are the links that
connect one project task to another,
and as we mentioned, they're often
the greatest source of risk to a project.
Two or more project tasks may have
a relationship with one another in which
the completion of one task is reliant
on the initiation of another task, and
vice versa.
Think of these tasks
like a line of dominoes
toppling each other over, one by one.
If one domino falls, it'll knock
the next one over and so on and so on.
For instance, a construction company may
have a number of jobs across the city.
Each project requires a foreman and
a project manager to be chosen before
the requirements, timeline, and budget
get signed off and the crew is chosen.
You wouldn't choose a crew and tell them
to get to work before the work has been
clearly scoped and
the contracts were signed.
That's an example of
an internal dependency,
which describes the relationship between
two tasks within the same project.
External dependencies, on the other hand,
refer to tasks that are reliant on outside
factors, like regulatory agencies or
other projects.
For instance, if a construction company
is scheduled to demolish a building site,
they'll have to wait until their
project is approved by the city.
External dependencies aren't always
in the project manager's control, but
it's important to be aware of them so
that the project stays on track.
Mandatory dependencies are tasks that
are legally or contractually required.
For instance, when that construction
company finishes the demolition and
starts the rebuild, they'll first have
to pour a concrete foundation and
then have it inspected by
the city to ensure it meets
their standards before the construction
company can continue to build.
Lastly, discretionary dependencies
are defined by the project team.
These are dependencies that
could occur on their own, but
the team saw a need to make those
dependencies reliant on one another.
For instance, the construction company may
be using concrete from a new supplier and
want to run a test,
pouring a portion of the foundation to
get a better estimate of the total amount
of product they'll need to complete the
foundation, rather than buying too much or
too little product up front.
The task of pouring a portion
of the foundation comes first,
because the team needed more
information before making a decision.
A project manager has to work diligently
to incorporate dependency management.
Dependency management is the process of
managing all of these interrelated tasks
and resources within the project
to ensure that your overall project is
completed successfully on time and
in budget.
To pursue effective dependency management,
there are four important steps
that a project manager can take:
proper identification, recording
dependencies, continuous monitoring and
control, and efficient communication.
The first step is proper identification.
A project manager will have to
brainstorm all possible project
dependencies with their team and
categorize them accordingly.
Next step is recording dependencies.
After all dependencies are identified,
a risk register should be created.
A risk register is a table or
chart that contains your list of risks and
dependencies.
The risk register should include
a description of the dependency,
the date, and all activities or tasks
that may be impacted by the dependency.
Then, a project manager will want to
maintain continuous monitoring and
control.
This means you will want to schedule
regular meetings to check in on
the interrelated tasks,
staying up-to-date on any progress
being made and double checking for
changes that will impact other tasks.
Last step is efficient communication.
Keeping the project team and stakeholders
updated can help resolve dependencies and
keep the project going strong.
To recap, we just discussed how to define
dependencies, both internal and external,
and we learned the importance of
managing and tracking dependencies.
We also discussed the importance of
clearly defining dependencies at
the project outset,
like in our foundation example,
and learned about dependency management.
In the next video,
we'll give you concrete techniques
to manage the risks in your project.
I'll meet you there.